MUHAMMAD ZIAD ABUSAA

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

+13 years experience of software development and +5 years of experience in DevOps and Cloud technologies. Well-versed in technology to create systems that are reliable and user-friendly. Skilled leader who has the proven ability to motivate, educate, and manage a team of professionals to build applications and effectively track changes.

WORK HISTORY

SENIOR DEVOPS ENGINEER LUCID MOTORS

14/5/2023 – Present



PRINCIPAL DEVOPS ENGINEER VISION BANK

1/1/2022 - 04-05-2023

- DevOps technologies and tooling selection and implementation.
- 2. Leading Cloud adoption in organization.
- 3. Leading GitOps implementation for applications using Argo CD.
- 4. Shifting security left: implemented security checks such as SAST and SCA in applications pipelines.
- 5. Quality code checks in pipelines using Sonarqube.
- 6. Working closely with our development team to create an automated continuous integration (CI) and continues delivery (CD)
- 7. Implemented monitoring using Prometheus and Grafana stack.
- 8. Infrastructure provisioning using Terraform.
- 9. Patching/upgrading tools and packages with latest versions.

- 10. Working closely with Cyber to apply the security requirements in applications and tools.
- Training and enabling new joiners in Platform and DevSecOps areas

PLATFORM LEAD (CLOUD NATIVE APPLICATIONS), THIQAH BUSINESS SERVICES



1/9/2019 - 30/12/2021

- 1. Leading software delivery projects for Governments clients (Design and Implementation).
- 2. Leading more than one team that overall consistent +10 people.
- 3. Leading transformation into Cloud native Apps.
- 4. Leading adopting Kubernetes / Containerization in entire company.
- 5. Participate and advise in projects Design/Architecture with Architecture team.
- 6. Adopting Agile, DevOps practices.
- 7. Backend APIs development

PRODUCT MANAGER / TEAM LEAD, NETWAYS, RIYADH



1/1/2018 - 1/8/2019

- 1. Team leader, responsible of project implementation and delivery and managing the dev team / following up on daily basis.
- 2. Reviewing the final product before shipping into customer, In terms of business and technical implementation.
- 3. Product management: responsible of managing product backlogs and first chair customer facing person.
- 4. Participate in application design with Architecture team.

TECHNICAL TEAM LEADER, NETWAYS, RIYADH



1/1/2017 - 30/12/2017

- Team leader, responsible of project implementation and delivery and managing the dev team / following up on daily basis.
- 2. Developing solutions using NET.
- 3. Building solutions using MS SharePoint.
- 4. Identifying and analyzing system requirements.
- 5. Defining project scope, and preparing analysis document.

SENIOR SOLUTION DESIGNER, NETWAYS, RIYADH

net ays

1/12/2012 - 1/1/2017

SOFTWARE ENGINEER, OGER SYSTEMS, RIYADH

1/1/2010 - 30/11/2012



PUBLISHED COURSES

Argo CD Essential Guide for End Users (Udemy)







CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner

validation #: N9YY5EB2WEEQ1M5Z



PCA: Prometheus Certified

Associate

Certification Number: LF-pp8k8uvy3s



Cloud Digital Leader Certification Number: xvCjoH

CKA: Certified Kubernetes

Administrator

Certification Number: LF-kg8hjq9m42



CKS: Certified Kubernetes Security

Specialist

CERTIFICATION NUMBER: LF-IJ4BDLK3O6



Page | 3

CKAD: Certified Kubernetes Application Developer

Certification Number: LF-4xr63e8hp8

Microsoft Certified: DevOps

Engineer Expert

Certification Number: H584-3759

Microsoft Certified: Azure

Developer Associate
Certification Number: H584-3619

Microsoft® Certified Solutions

Expert: Productivity

Certification Number: G421-5726

Microsoft® Certified Solutions

Associate: Office 365

Certification Number: G421-5525

Microsoft Certified Professional Certification Number: E933-3478













SKILLS

- Containers orchestration / Kubernetes. "CKA, CKS and CKAD"
- Oracle Cloud.
- Google Cloud: Cloud Digital Leader
- Azure DevOps. "Certified"
- DevSecOps.
- Helm Charts: Building and maintaining.
- GitOps: Argo CD
- Teleport for PAM
- Building IaC using Terraform.
- Version control systems such as Azure DevOps and Gitlab.
- Secrets management using Vault
- Observability: Prometheus / Grafana / Alert manager.
- Rancher.
- Team management / leadership
- .NET Core / Framework.
- Client Side Development

- SharePoint "Certified"
- Office 365 Understanding
- CRM Understanding
- BizTalk Understanding
- K2 Understanding
- Angular
- Project Scoping
- Application design
- Preparing demos and related presentation
- Product owner / scrum master / solution management
- System / Business analysis

PROFESSIONAL ACHIEVEMENTS

PLATFORM AND TRANSFORMATION

- Building production ready platform around cloud native ecosystem.
- Building Toolchain for DevSecOps.
 - Git and CI & CD tools.
 - Monitoring tools.
 - Secrets management tools.
 - Security tools for DevSecOps.
- Leading organization transformation using cloud native ecosystem.
- Applying security best practices related to systems, clusters and applications.
- Built multiple k8s clusters managed and "self hosted" for multi environments including production environment.

INTERNET AND ESERVICES PROJECTS

- Amaaly: .NET Core / Docker / Kubernetes.
- Ministry of commerce / Franchise : .NET Core / Angular

Page | 5 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa

- Ministry of commerce / Maroof : .NET Core / Docker and Kubernetes .
- SFDA eservices project : .Net Core , Kubernetes , React
- Ministry of interior Mifon Project : Angular JS , Web Api , SharePoint , CRM
- GMCO internet website : SharePoint 2013 , Word Automation
- The centennial fund eServices website (eServices using .Net)
- Alrajhi Takaful Internet website (eServices using .Net)
- Council of Saudi Chambers Internet website : SharePoint 2010
- High Commission for the Development of Arrivadh website: SharePoint 2010

ERP

RDCCI ERP web application (using asp.net web forms)

INTRANET PROJECTS

- Sanabil Intranet : SharePoint 2016 / CMS
- SASO Intranet: SharePoint 2010 / .Net / AngularJs / K2
- Ecra intranet: SharePoint 2013 / Word Automation
- GMCO intranet : SharePoint 2013 / CMS
- COE enterprise content management system : SharePoint
- Riyadh Chamber of Commerce Intranet : SharePoint 2010

EDUCATION

BACHELOR IN COMPUTER SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF JORDAN, AMMAN

2005-2009

Page | 6 Muhammad Ziad Abusaa